A Guide to the Barbara Woodward Architectural Collection 1966-1992, n.d.
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Barbara Woodward Architectural Collection 1966-1992
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms2003-016
One container, two oversize folders; 1.75 cu. ft.
Architectural papers of Barbara Woodward, Residential Remodeling Designer. Includes specifications, materials lists, correspondence, photographs and drawings relating to Woodward's design activities on various residential remodeling projects.
Barbara Woodward
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to the public.
Acquisition Information
The Barbara Woodward Architectural Collection was donated to the Special Collections at Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University by the creator in September 2003.
Biographical/Historical Information
Barbara Woodward took classes in architecture as an undergraduate at the University of California at Berkeley. She graduated in 1949, after which time she occupied various positions in the architectural field. One of her early positions was in a San Francisco construction firm that built a naval hospital on Guam. Later she worked as a Junior Architect and then as a Senior Architect at Kaisers Engineers during the building of an aluminum plant in Chalmette, Louisiana. After taking time off to start and raise a family, Woodward returned to the architectural field and worked on residential working drawings at the firm of two former classmates. At this point, she began a career in residential remodeling design, which proceeded to span from 1966 to 1991. As a residential remodeling designer, Woodward's projects included kitchen and bath remodels, interior and exterior renovations, as well as room and second story additions. Her clients were initially comprised of her neighbors, and eventually came to include those who were referred by other clients and contractors. Woodward eventually ceased her work as a residential remodeling designer in 1991.
Scope and Content Information
The collection consists of drawings, sketches, photographs, specifications, materials lists, correspondence, memoranda, and notes. The collection relates to Woodward's design activities on various residential remodeling projects in Berkeley, Oakland and San Francisco, California during the time period from 1966 to 1992.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into one series of Project Records and two subseries of Files and Drawings.
I. Project Records, 1966-1992. The series consists of records created by Woodward during the course of her work on various projects as a residential designer. Projects primarily include designs for residential remodeling, as well as designs for renovations, alterations, and additions to residences. Other projects include designs for seismic retrofitting and area use planning. The records include drawings, sketches, specifications, notes, material lists, photographs, memoranda, and correspondence. The series is arranged into two subseries, Subseries A. Files and Subseries B. Drawings. Subseries are arranged chronologically by client.
Contents List
- Series I. Project Records, 1966-1992
  - Subseries A. Files, 1966-1992
    - Holton, Entry Patio Renovation, 1966 (Box-folder 1-1)
    - Simpson, Basement Remodeling, 1969 (Box-folder 1-2)
    - Simpson, Deck addition, 1970 (Box-folder 1-3)
    - Simpson, Living room alterations, 1971 (Box-folder 1-4)
    - Simpson, Kitchen and bathroom alterations, 1977 (Box-folder 1-5)
    - Simpson, Front porch remodeling, 1978 (Box-folder 1-6)
    - Simpson, Master bedroom, 1979-1980 (Box-folder 1-7)
    - Simpson, Carport, 1983 (Box-folder 1-8)
    - Simpson, Ground floor addition, 1986-1987 (Box-folder 1-9)
    - Simpson, Residential alterations, 1989 (Box-folder 1-10)
    - McGuire, Kitchen remodeling and porch alterations, 1972 (Box-folder 1-11)
    - Olander, Deck addition, laundry relocation, and kitchen remodeling, 1973-1975 (Box-folder 1-12)
    - Olander, Second-floor remodeling, 1977 (Box-folder 1-13)
    - Olander, Living room and dining room alterations, 1981 (Box-folder 1-14)
    - Olander, Study, 1987 (Box-folder 1-15)
    - Spear, Kitchen renovations, 1981-1982 (Box-folder 1-16)
    - Rooney, Kitchen and laundry remodeling, 1983 (Box-folder 1-17)
    - Levenson, Alterations and kitchen renovation, 1987-1988, 1991 (Box-folder 1-18)
    - Clemens, Basement bathroom renovation, deck addition, and seismic retrofit, 1988-1992 (Box-folder 1-19)
  - Subseries B. Drawings, 1966-1991
    - Project drawings, 1966-1990 (Oversize 1)
      Plans, elevations, sections, and studies relating to various residential remodeling projects, including projects for Olander, Lysmer, and Dimitriou residences among others.
    - Simpson drawings, 1969-1984 (Oversize 2)
      Plans, elevations, sections, and details relating to various projects for Simpson residence.